Okay, so in this video then,
and in fact in the next few
videos, we are going to be
covering the Critical Path method.
Now the Critical Path method is a way of
developing your schedule, and there's
several different ways of developing a
project schedule.
Critical Path is just
one of them, and that is
the one that they ask
about for the PMP exam.
Alright, so let's just go straight into
the Critical Path method, let's just
explain first what the Critical Path
Method actually is.
Now the critical path method then,
as I said, it's a way of developing the
schedule and there are five basic steps
involved, right?
These five basic steps here.
Now, there are other steps involved as
well, but when you understand that these
five basic steps, all of the other steps
start falling into place.
Okay, so the basic steps are.
So let's go through the
basic steps and then there are
some terms on here that I'm
going to explain and define.
Okay, so first step is to calculate the
critical path, right?
That's the first step, calculate the
critical path.
Again, I'm going to explain what critical
path means in just a second.
Second step is to note that float on
critical path is going to be zero.
Initially, it's going to be zero.
Now, so that's truly not really a step,
but something I want to explain there.
So let's just, you know, hold your thought
on that.
We'll come back to that just a second.
third step is to calculate the early start
and early finish for each activity right
for each activity we want to calculate the
early start and the early finish and that
process is known as the forward pass the
fourth step is then to calculate the late
finish and late start in the order again
of each activity and that sounds like if
you're calculating the late
finish and the late start looks
like you know well are we
going backwards Indeed, we are.
That's why it's known as the backward
pass.
And then the fifth and
final step is to calculate
the float on the
non-critical path activities.
Okay.
All right, so these are the five basic
steps.
Now, let's explain what does that actually
mean.
Well, first of all, why are we going
through all of this?
Well, we need to know when is the project
going to start, when is
a project going to end?
And in order to know the start and the
end, we need to know what actually
activities we have in place, how many
activities we have in place, right?
What are the dependencies between each
activity?
So, one activity is dependent on another
activity, so this activity has to be done
before another activity, so we need to
know all that, which activities can be run
in parallel, and then plus we need to know
how long activities are going to take,
right, so that we can determine the
overall schedule.
Plus, at the same time, when we are trying
to, say, plan our
resources on our activity.
We need to know when we're going to plan
to be planning our resources.
If we have an activity that is not going
to start until this time next year, right?
Well, that might not be
really urgent to start planning
all of the resources for
that activity right now.
So when should we start planning our
resources and so and so forth?
So, you know, it gives an overall picture
of your timeline, an overall picture of
all of your activities, so you can plan
accordingly.
So you can plan for each activity,
you can plan the earliest we can start an
activity, the earliest we can finish
without it impacting the schedule,
and the latest we can
start and the latest we
can finish without it
impacting the schedule.
Sorry, let's talk about this term here.
Float.
Float is the same thing as slack or
cushion.
It's basically how long can an activity be
delayed?
Now, this is not a delay meaning that
you're going behind schedule.
This is a delay meaning that it's inbuilt
into the schedule.
It's already inherent in the schedule.
So you've got two activities, right?
One activity takes longer than another
activity.
right, well, the shorter activity can be
delayed in some way.
This is inherently inbuilt into the
schedule.
How long can that activity be delayed?
That is known as float.
Critical path, on the
other hand, critical path
represents the longest
path through a network.
It's the longest path and it represents
the earliest completion date.
It represents the shortest time to
complete the project.
project, the earliest completion date.
So critical path is always considered the
longest path through a network.
Now, initially, that sounds like a
contradiction in terms.
It's the longest path and the shortest
time to complete the project.
Well, let's think about this.
Let's say we have two activities.
Only two activities and both activities
can be run in parallel.
Both will start at the same time,
they're independent of one another.
You've got two separate teams
working on these two activities
and they can be done, they
can start at the same time.
One activity is going to take five days.
Another activity is going to take 20 days.
So when is the earliest we can complete
the project?
Naturally 20 days.
That's the earliest we can complete the
project.
If you've got two activities, one taking
five days, one's taking 20 days,
well we can't finish in five days because
the other activity has to take 20 days.
So the earliest we can finish this project
is 20 days, right?
So 20 days then would be considered the
critical path.
Right.
So the second activity is on the critical
path.
So it's a longest path and it represents
the shortest duration for the project.
It's a longest path.
It represents the earliest completion
date.
The earliest completion, in this case,
20 days.
Now, this first activity, that's going to
take five days.
Right, well, it's going to take five days.
Now we're just hanging around for 15 days
for the second activity to complete.
So technically then, this first activity
can be delayed by up to 15 days,
and that's going to have no impact on the
schedule.
If it gets delayed a few days,
no big deal.
it can be delayed back to 15 days,
and there'll be no impact on the schedule.
That 15 days is known as the float,
right?
That is a slack or cushion that is inbuilt
into the schedule.
So that, now for purpose
of critical path method,
they don't always call
it a slack or a cushion.
They call it a float.
Right, so this first activity has a float
of 15 days.
It's inbuilt into the schedule.
The second activity,
that's going to take 20
days, how long can
that activity be delayed?
What if that activity is delayed?
Right, well, the whole principle behind
critical path is that any activity that is
on the critical path is going to have a
zero float.
Initially, it will have a zero float.
When you're calculating critical path,
right?
When you're calculating
the schedule, you always
calculate the critical
path as having a zero float.
No slack, no cushion.
Right, so in my example here, our project
is going to take 20 days.
If that second activity
is delayed in any way,
that's going to be a
delay on the entire project.
So that second activity that is on the
critical path has a zero float.
So initially, when
we're calculating critical
path, it's going to have a zero float.
Now, we're going to talk about positive
float and negative float.
So generally, critical path
is the longest path through
the network, and it will
have the smallest float.
Whatever is the smallest float,
that will be the critical path.
So this is just an introduction then.
In the subsequent videos, we are going to
follow each of these steps.
We're going to follow
each of these steps to
go through a whole critical path exercise.